the real aim of this attack was to
eternalize war to prevent any
possibility for decades of Peace what
horrifies me is there are two narratives
opposed radical which in a an uncanny
terrifying way Echo each other those who
now appear as the opposite poles are
really playing a very similar game what
I fear terribly is that in the long term
all Sites will be losers now is the
moment for Israel yeah a uh annihilate
Hamas but at the same time reach out to
Palestinians giving them some kind of a
clear clear program of Hope slav welcome
back to politics Joe um for those
unfamiliar with who you are how would
you like to introduce
yourself
ah now comes a surprise I still Advocate
communism but what kind of communism a
German journalist asked me what kind of
communist you are and I gave an answer a
moderat
conservative communist by moderately
conservative I mean something very
precise you know what bothers me with
some leftist liberals they make big plan
you know let's do this new legislation
and so on but not with Rishi sunak kind
but with authentic their endangered
species today old conservatives what
even Lenin and Ma admired in them is
this brutal realism you know in the
sense of yes we can do this but you
think like crazy about what will be the
consequences what we if we screw that
other thing and and so on and so because
isn't the standard even radical leftist
game then you of course cause a
catastrophe and then you blame the enemy
you know it's like what I call sadly in
Africa the Mugabe game you screw it up
and then you blame ah because secretly
the whites still control everything and
what is really breaking my heart is that
now South Africa is approaching the so
by moderately conservative I mean simply
before you act think well about all
possible consequences because social
life here I am very pessimist not
traditional Marxist is uh is obscure
non-transparent complex you never know
what the actual result would be so now
you can Counterattack me but why then
communist at all to give you a very
short answer it's a not a communism of
Joy uh abundance it's a sad pessimist
communism look we are facing now 3 four
five I cannot even nominate them all
real apocalyptic threats
War
immigration ecological threat artificial
intelligence and I don't see
any other way to cope with this than
what I provocatively call War communism
an emergency state where I'm not talking
about world government and state taking
over that would be a catastrophe even
worse but some kind of global
international cooperation not just this
aesthetic cooperation yes we must
understand each but more forceful Co
cooperation will be necessary now when
people tell me oh but this is total
Utopia I tell them sorry remember Co
even Trump had to do measures which come
very close to what I call communism you
remember uh every family got a check for
$2,000 and so on stimulus checks yeah
yeah and uh you remember
how half a year before if you if you
were to mention an idea like this all
the neoliberals would say no this would
mean ruin of our economy no it didn't
the good point about coid epidemics was
that it was made clear how much we can
play with the market do things
independently of the market and they
don't necessarily ruin the economy so
again communist it means I sincerely
don't see how to cope with the problems
threats that are on the
horizon without a much stronger
Collective collaboration well beyond the
limits of The Sovereign Nation State
just to conclude please allow me this my
example that I mention all the time you
remember two and a half years ago uh
that crazy hot summer where uh Northwest
of United States Southwest of of Canada
Seattle Vancouver 50°
C it was warmer than Mumbai or
emirats you cannot say they should take
care more of ecology no these are rich
parts of the words they did the proper
measures the problem is that the whole
circulation of air around the North Pole
is Disturbed so in this sense I'm a
communist in the sense of we have to
prepare to some emergency State
precisely because if we don't do it in a
transparent Democratic way then better
not to think what can happen but again
moderately conservative be careful about
the consequences I hate again this
traditional leftist game was yeah yeah
imperialism still controls us and so on
mhm so the reason we're talking is
because of this book what lies ahead
when there is no future you talk them
the threats you mentioned there war
climate catastrophe those things of that
nature that it's important that we have
to conceptualize and understand these
catastrophes in order to avert them most
recently and I think the most prominent
example of any of those currently is the
war in Israel the bombing of Gaza and I
wondered if you could talk a little bit
about how we need to conceptualize that
conflict in order to understand it and
in order to avert the possible
catastrophe that contains as you outline
in the book
uh it's the question which I'm almost
afraid to answer because it's all the
time on my mind maybe you or some of our
viewers know it I two weeks ago I was in
Frankfurt book fair and I practically
caused a scandal addressing this issue
all the big media big Daily News papers
attack me as practically anti-semitic
supporting terrorists although the first
sentence of my speech was Hamas did a
horrible crime Israel has the right to
annihilate it and all my B is but we all
know that in the background there
is the unresolved status of the
Palestinians there are over 4 million
people on the west Bank in Gaza in
Israel itself in uh in East Jerusalem
and they live in I cannot by call it
ontological limbo it's not clear what
they are even the name of the territory
is not clear is it is it as is for the
Hardline Zionist is it Judea and Samaria
is it Palestine is it West Bank or
whatever and this people are in a
horrible position and without
justifying the brutal Hamas attack I
condemned it ruthlessly now maybe you
cut out if you want this I let me tell
you a story which really hit me I'm in
close contact with Palestinians and with
uh West Bank and not only West Bank Jews
and they told me you know why some of
them leftists especially were so hurt by
the Hamas attack because that area of
that famous famous terrible R party
where Hamas was doing the murdering at
kots there do you know that this
were I don't know them but I know people
who knew people who were massacred them
these were the most Progressive Jews
they all the time had contact with Gaza
helping them hiring them to help them
taking into hospital and things like
that yeah yeah it's incredible and this
tells a lot about why did Hamas attack
there not only because it was most
practical but
unfortunately because the real aim of
this attack was to eternalize war to
prevent any possibility for decades of
peace and it's breathtaking how with all
all absolutely unambiguous condemnation
of Hamas when I just said but can't you
see the terrible PR predicament of
Palestinians who are now in one or
another way under Israeli control they
are now
explicitly not uh treated as a second
class citizens whole series of things
they cannot do and so on and as I always
mention this name if you want a symbol
of what Israel is doing now Israel the
state I mean just the government now
remember the name itamar Ben G who was
20 years ago or when condemned by
Israeli courts as a potential terrorist
racist and so on this guy is now it
sounds like a bad joke this guy is now
Minister for public sec Purity or
whatever and it's uh I learned this from
friends on the West Bank how uh public
order is falling around settlers
attacking it's slow but continuous
ethnic cleansing I think that
uh what horrifies me is there are two
narratives opposed radical which in a an
uncanny ter in way Echo each other on
the one hand I agree there is the Hamas
narrative their leader Han who said
message to Israel go out we will kill
you if you remain you don't belong here
but then if you look at the first
principle officially published of the
new Netanyahu government is all of
Jewish land they exclude Judea
Samaria Golan hes and so on is
exclusively a Jewish land so it's
symmetrical idea of there is no place
for the other so uh I think that the key
Point here is not to fall into this trap
of Palestinians versus Israeli but to
see how those who now appear as the
opposite poles are really playing very
similar game and then I did something
let's not lose too much time
which cost even more of a scandal I warn
them that there is in the West in the
western
anti-Semitism a long tradition I'm not
inventing crazy terms of you cannot but
call it Zionist
anti-Semitism do you remember that guy
who shot 1890 Norwegian leftist brav he
says he said here we have too many Jews
throw them out but Israel it's a wall
against Oriental barbarism we should
fully support Israel you know who began
this I couldn't believe it Reinhard
hyrich the father of the Holocaust he
said he wrote I quote I don't know if
it's in this book of another there are
two types of
juus uh uh integration ju who wants to
blend into our society and Zionist
ju in this juice who wants to integrate
into our society we have to get rid of
them but if J moveed to Palestine we
could have wonderful collaboration of
them and so on and so on and the same
thing goes on now uh Trump is doing the
same Trump supports Israel there but in
United States you know proud boys and so
on he is supported by explicitly
anti-semitic again so I will conclude
quickly just with one point which is
important I think to understand properly
the ongoing War it's to take into
account its catastrophic effect in
Israel itself there was a moment of Hope
in Israel a couple of months ago you
remember that big conflict hundreds of
thousands of people opposing this new
legislation which basically abolishes
the independent legal structure and so
on and this war now serves perfectly
Netanyahu government now we forget about
that and so on and so on so what I fear
terribly is that in the long term all
sides will be losers in in the sense
that uh uh I am very
sensitive
a propo anti-Semitism I recognize it
whatever it is and I think the first
thing that will happen is anti-Semitism
was still now a mostly European and a
little bit Middle East but mostly
European American phenomenon now
anti-Semitism will become a worldwide
movement in a
totally disgusting way
it will be a new Link in this series of
what I call Unholy alliances for example
you remember what happened in Uganda
half a half a year ago I think where
their parliament democratically of
course uh imposed the most terrifying
anti-gay law if you are caught in
homosexual act the punishment can be
death yeah but you know how they
Justified it a struggle against Colonia
ISM and what I am so afraid is that
anti-Semitism will be included into this
series like to be anti-semitic means to
be for for the third world suffering
Nations and so on this will be a
catastrophe even if in the short term
Israel wins
there and I think this was the idea of
Hamas we may lose here yeah not they
they will escape the ordinary people
but but it will give birth to such a new
way of anti-Semitism not only in the
Arab world then the game Putin is
playing here who is counting on this
equation Israel is like Ukraine a
colonialist western dominated nation and
so on and so on this is quite
catastrophic the only hope I see there
are reasonable voices I'm in contact
with them although we are politically
not on the same side and he doesn't go
far enough but for example Yuval Harari
that guy Hoda he said something which is
very important she said there is no
peace in the Middle East without
Palestinians being allowed to live free
dignified life in their Homeland he
meant Westbank and so on and it's very
important that he used the term in their
Homeland this is also their home
so it's to utopian but now it is growing
stronger in Israel this idea for which I
was attacked as an anti-semitic in all
left Israeli media you find it now
that now is the moment for Israel yeah
uh annihilate Hamas but at the same time
reach out to
Palestinians giving
them uh uh some kind of a clear clear
program of Hope listen here we can make
a deal you can leave safely here and so
on and so on to continue the theme of
catastrophe yeah you've also described
the Western response to the conflict a
moral catastrophe could you talk about
that a little bit more oh
uh the problem was that
uh now it's getting more mixed but this
you know I was interrupted
in my Frankfort speech yeah so because
uh the basic problem
was but I even didn't use the word but
like I condemn Hamas but Y and as
somebody says at the end of the debate
the word but should be prohibited now
another word that should be prohibited I
was informed is complex situation now
there is only one side it's absolutely
clear and you know where I see a moral
catastrophe now I'm sorry if I will
become anti sound anti- German I don't
mean all of Germany I mean the
predominant stance in politics now it's
this one Germans admit they did the
Holocaust and now by pursuing radically
pro-israeli politics they do something
disgusting I think they think that by
supporting Israel where Israel is not
right West Bank and so on they will
somehow pay their debt for the Holocaust
and so on I find this something so
terribly immoral another thing that I
find immoral is also and at multiple
levels and I here only quote yal Harari
and all of them this this is for me the
true moral catastrophe where you posit a
choice either you speak about uh Israeli
victims or you speak about Palestinian
victims in Gaza if you mention
Palestinian victims you are already anti
itic and so on and so on
my my basic Insight here is that's why I
think it's a moral catastrophe that
those Zionist Israelis who mention in
today's situation Holocaust are doing a
terrifying disrespectful exploitation of
Holocaust itself Holocaust A terrifying
unimaginable crime they use it as a
stake as a Tong to justify their Pol
politics now that's why I think that and
did you notice this detail that's why so
many people attacked me I was very
restrained and careful in my Frankfurt
speech all the positive people I quote
that were Jews even mosha Dian who how
much more refreshing it's now to read
the first generation benan diai who
didn't play the game This Is Our Land
blah blah blah no they said it's a
impossible conflict we know nobody's
right and so on not to mention Simon
vental not to
mention my true ethical hero if there is
a person whom I would to whom I would
give Maybe please to our listeners check
it on Wikipedia rever is M Edelman it's
a polish jew Mega hero
he was a bundist more socialist Jew he
was one of the key organizers of the
ghetto Uprising 43 in warso magically he
survived it then he was one of the key
organ organizers of the uh warso
Uprising
44 magically he survived it then he
remained in Poland and he gave a
wonderful theoretical explanation when
later anti-em is M under communism
emerged again he stayed there and he
again he provided a beautiful metaphor
he
said it's not what I'm saying but
imagine me as a stone in
aitz somebody has to be here to embody
not to talk about that memory and at the
end of his life he wrote a letter to my
Palestinian friends where he said I
support your Rebellion against Israel of
course condemning all Palestinian
violence there is a great Jewish
tradition which is incredible that's why
I don't like this Western this the most
disgusting Western position anti-semitic
Zionist of not too many Jews here but
you go there and protect our
civilization no I like Jews here also
wherever they are they make a great
contribution to our civilization and so
on look precisely because they were
stateless we cannot even imagine
European modernity Enlightenment and so
on without the juw the very idea of
Enlightenment
universalism came from the Jews who
simply like they were condemned to be
Universalist you know but you know where
the
sorry just one thing which may you know
Netanyahu and others when you ask them
why
is that place Palestine yours they
said it's look at the Bible it tells
everything and so on but in the most
ironic case of cancel culture mention
the Bible and you will be excluded as
anti-semitic once I did this in a debate
in New York I think some grw said but
sorry we are attached to our tradition
look at the Bible so I told them I
quoted him I said yes let's look at the
Bible you know Moses 40 years wandering
around uh siai then up on the mountain
Moses dies he already sees the valley
and then Joshua takes over and what to
do and God's voice tells him Canan
canites are down there they are evil
people kill them all men women children
and and so on so you know if I were a
Jew I wouldn't insist too much on the
Bible you know but to avoid a
misunderstanding I'm not here condemning
uh the Jews because at that time let's
be frank everybody was acting like this
we Slavs from some Siberian steps I
don't know where how did we come to
Europe by invading it and so on at that
so I'm just saying that uh that uh in
the same way that we talk about invented
traditions we should also treat our uh
historical documents and uh now I will
make a very sad
conclusion I am very skeptical about
this idea that originally religions are
good
Islam Judaism
Christianity it's only in their
political application that they are that
they are misused no you find a lot of
horror and cheat already in the original
so I'm here much more of
a pessimist the lesson of this I
immedately conclude sorry the lesson of
this is
we are left to our own resources in
lenan terms theoretical there is no big
other by big other I don't mean just God
but some Global symbolic order which
tells you what to do no we live in a
very dangerous era where no reference to
tradition or to science or whatever can
tell us what to do I'd also um in the
tradition of kind of you know
emancipatory Judaism encourage listeners
to consult the Wikipedia of Dennis
Goldberg who was impris imprisoned on
Robin Island um and actually separated
he was um part of the anti-ap paride
campaign in South Africa and also in
prison there with Mandela but of course
separated from him because of apartheid
and so was alone in prison for the same
period of time why because he was a Jew
or what because Mandela was was black
right and he was a Jew he was white so
the yeah because I know I I sorry to
interrupt this may be I know the
situation there very well you know even
uh now in India many people many some
people many don't know about me hate me
because I killed or at least undermined
the respect for another sacred cow there
Gandhi you know when Gandhi was in India
yes he fought against aart heite but
only for the Indian minority read
Gandhi's text my friends republish them
now he doesn't put in doubt the big
separation black white
he just says we Indians should be
counted as white and so on the second
thing you see this is what I mean uh uh
moderately conservative maybe you read
it I think I already used this somewhere
a couple of months ago at burbeck
College where I'm temporarily employed
there was a debate with a lady from
South Africa uh Hardline
oldc fighter and I asked her a Frank
question question I asked her in all our
media I read all the time about how
South Africa is on the border of
becoming a fail on the edge of becoming
a failed State blah blah blah I don't
want to believe Western media please
tell me how do I reply to this and I was
almost crying so s you know what she
told me she told me that more and more
the predominant
atmosphere feeling uh in the poor black
majority poor is Nostalgia for
aparte she said that now in memory they
remember apart as a time where yes they
were second class citizens but if
anything the standard of fing was the
same maybe a little bit even higher for
the poor black majority plus it was a
police state which means there was
safety now Society is disintegrating
South Africa Amica is has one of the
highest rape numbers per capita you see
this is what I want the left to avoid
how this eternal stories look at Latin
America Bolivia but now they did not do
a wise thing they cut diplomatic ties
with Israel but till now I believed in
Bolivia because I was friendly with vice
president of Morales Alvaro Garcia
linera and so on they were 12 years in
power with without scaring too much the
capital they succeeded the standard of
leing will up and then you remember
there was a good against them but they
won again so I that's my uh uh that's my
moderate conservative Vision how to
avoid I will name just three names Cuba
Venezuela Nicaragua where it was a
catastrophy the left has to ask very
hard questions here I don't want to be
that comfortable leftist who organizes a
revolution a revolution fails and then
you move back to your academic post and
write a thick book how because of the
imperialist cunningness and plot it had
to fail the revolution no the left
deserves
some authentic success can we
interrogate a little bit more the role
of violence in Revolution in Liberation
struggle whether it's you know as we
were talking about the anti-apartheid
campaign in South Africa or um well take
any any sort of struggle against
Injustice the one we've been we've been
interrogating so far is obviously with
Palestine and
Israel is there an
acceptable level of violence to your
mind in a Liberation struggle I I no no
no I'm not naive here I know that in
certain
conditions uh if nothing else a certain
level of violence paradoxically creates
the conditions for a peaceful Revolution
I forgot the guy's name I'm old cile but
a guy a black guy I think wrote a
wonderful book I quote it I forgot where
in so new text where he says that look
for example at American uh in the 60s
and so on struggle Against
Racism uh yes Martin Luther King won but
it also won because it was clear to the
white majority there if there is not a
threat of violence behind Luther King
wouldn't be taken seriously you know you
did it was the same in South Africa yes
Mandela won but because the apite guys
were well aware that there was a much
more radical orientation with did
thec threatening with violence the most
tragic example here let's look into
history is
Haiti where uh I mean the exploitation
of Haiti till the hati revolution around
1800 was breathtaking let's say that
profits from Haiti brought to the French
State more than half of its income but
what I want to say is this Revolution
was one the first generation to S lure
were very fair towards the whites they
just fre slaves but their main worry was
to keep the production going economic
collapse to invoid then the French
Napoleon is here the bad guy he brought
arrested to S lur brought him to France
and slowly killed him in an abandoned
castle blah blah then the next
generation were more radical violent uh
you know what they did they
uh I forgot his name the successor of
toen lur he simply gave an order to kill
all white people who remained there with
one exception that's true polls Polish
people you know the story it's one of
the most beautiful revolutionary Legend
it again makes me cry when Napoleon sent
an AR Army to hati with a horrible order
kill all the blacks he said after the
revolution it's not just to insave them
again kill them all bring New Slaves
then when the French army was
approaching the hati black Army
revolutionaries they heard some singing
and they thought yeah this must be some
primitive African dancing when they come
closer you know what they recognize you
know what the black fre slaves were
singing
lar and thousands of Polish soldiers
said wait a minute are we here on the
right side and they change sides and so
Napoleon won but
then the result of all this trauma was
this terrifying order to kill all white
people now you can say you see if you
give them Freedom what happens ah it's
more complex because at precisely this
moment the New Black rulers took over
imitated perfectly the the French
aristocratic system they named counts
and so on you know they this violence
serves the establishment as a pure copy
of European FAL aristocracy there but ha
nonetheless did something prohibited and
to do you know that to be reintegrated
in into World economy hati had to
pay to France as for the damage of Lost
Property
slaves uh in throughout 19th century it
was at some point up to 80% its state
budget you know when the
last money was paid to France in
1947 I think so it consciously they kept
but so I don't avoid your question I
would put it like this first my limit is
uh if they're not well known as a
gangster family or what don't attack
civilian population keep it to Army
there if the situation is really
terrorist I condone a limited amount of
violence but we should always be aware
again of this uh
ambiguity that you know you need a
violent wink so that violence should be
more used as a threat to do the
necessary compromise that would be my
formula you WR but Counterattack me I
w't screw you I mean you just agree do
you don't did I say anything that you
don't agree please I would like to it's
actually funny because large parts of
what you said I do agree with I
part go to small
parts you done I think there has I think
there has to be you know so let's
interrogate sort of modern conflicts the
nature of modern conflict it's
asymmetrical always whether it's the
British and American Imperial forces in
Afghanistan whether it's the
Palestinians against the Israelis yeah
but Cas is sorry and and to say that the
Palestinians should confront the
Israelis militarily it's essentially a
death sentence yeah isn't it is to say
yeah and you can say great fantastic
morally justifiable but completely
ineffective as a tactic and it makes me
uncomfortable because what I'm
essentially saying what I'm the the the
place I'm left in is essentially
justifying the attack on civilians which
something morally ethically for me I
find deeply distressing deeply upsetting
and I and I but I don't see any other
way in terms of you know an effective
military campaign an effective terrorist
campaign the use of limited violence to
achieve political ends you know if they
attack military bases they will all die
so what else can they do if not kill the
civilians and I I find that deeply
deeply uncomfortable because like I said
okay now I will accept this totally
pragmatic ruthless thinking but
shouldn't have then focus a little bit
more on some effectively violent groups
of settlers or whatever and not
precisely that part which was closest
which was closest to them in some sense
yeah
I mean here I agree with you let's begin
by this the situation is tragic in some
sense you cannot propose a simple
solution and so like this is the formula
and so on uh uh no I see your point of
course but again as you already pointed
out not only this means suicide for
Palestinians but in the long term
such suicidal
attacks eternalize war and I don't see
then any peaceful ANC Mandela or
whatever arising out of this and
bringing peace that's what horrifies me
you know I would even accept attacks
here we agree if there is a hope for the
deil serve the way the threat with
violence was necessary to bring in
Mandela to bring in Martin Luther King
and so on otherwise I what really as
friend of the Jews and of Palestinians
I I see really it scares me again a new
wave of
anti-Semitism it
will I I don't trust zionists but I also
see very clearly anti-Semitism where
there is one and what I'm again what
horrifies me is this
identification of that anti-Semitism as
the result of this war will be elevated
into one of the main markers of
anticolonial struggle although you know
again I like to complicate things the
Jewish site is not clean here you know I
did something cunning I read Theodore
Herz
founder of ZM you know that he you know
to whom good for his soul he didn't send
it but you know that he wrote a letter
to cesil roads I did not know that
asking him for advice like and would he
invest
money addressing him in terms of
colonization you colonized half of
Africa help us to colonize it there
second thing he explicitly flirted her
already with the Western right using
these terms of today's right that a
state of Israel a Jewish State there
will beat an impregnable wall to to uh
to protect Western Europe from Oriental
barbarism so that's the mega tragedy of
of Zionism that what the
greatest victims of European
anti-Semitism chose the way to oppress
others there and got caught into this
way here I I hated Ahmad you know the ex
president of Iran I even at some
point was prohibited to enter because
there were some elections 10 years ago
where Ahmad ja won by cheating and so on
and I wrote some letters but you know
when he said something that others also
said okay Germans did something horrible
which Amed didn't admit but let's admit
it
Holocaust isn't there something cheating
in giving them the land in wouldn't it
be normal for Germans listen end of
World War II you also have a lot of
victims which means empty land give why
don't you you who killed six million
Jews give him I don't know the city of
Hamburg and you know there is some
cheating in it as if you know as if I I
borrow from you $1
billion and then instead of paying you
back I say take that guy's money you
know the situation is desperately
complex this is why this is not a
pessimism the starting point is there is
no clean solution here and as you know
as well as the word but complex
situation is a band band phrase in this
conversation as you said at the
beginning especially by this now
rediscovered is totally
pro-israeli po yeah they you know an
article in I forgot which German Daily
Newspaper attacking
me uh uh said uh you they put it as a
title of their text uh uh uh Hamas has
no context like it's Madness like you
know every mention of context is but
then I answered in I think quite that
even if we it's more complex just
condemn Hamas of course we should
inquire into context because for example
there are dozens hundreds of books of
the origins of Nazism and it's clear
that there was a crisis in Germany
experienced by millions of people
economic crisis and so on and Hitler
profited from that crisis offering a
certain anti-semitic narrative and to
many Ordinary People things were all of
a sudden clear you know like ah now we
know behind all of these are the juice
and so on so here is a nice example of
how
contextualizing doesn't mean justifying
in any way evil can be radical crazy
evil but it's always a product of
certain circumstances it exploded in
certain circumstances like the same
again in hati the second generation who
killed all the white people yes I agree
it was horrible but let's take a look at
how breathtaking the exploitation in
Haiti was
okay I will not go on I talk too much no
not at all not at all I think there's
one other sort of area I'd like to
explore on Israel Palestine before we
maybe move toor that's a terrible om is
it no no no leave it there leave it
there that's where it belongs face down
the Flor yeah yeah yeah yeah no I'm
always cynical to against myself is that
or to put it in more humanist terms
books are that objects we talk like
humans the book let's Okay so between
the two extremes the two totalitarian
positions that we've discussed the one
of Hamas and the one of benav and
smotri uh that sort ofri is the other
hard hard right Zionist position but
it's not just only Zionist let me S is
that their solution is this land is only
ours there is no place for exactly this
this sort of Greater Israel idea right
the expulsion of the Palestinians from
Gaza and if you look at demographic
changes happening in Israel the younger
generation skew much more to that
extreme right-wing politics they they
skew much more towards the politics of
the likes of benav and smotri and that
surely means looking to the Future
whether there's a solution whether
without sounding like Tony Blair a third
way somewhere in between those two total
extreme poles because the Israeli
population electorally is going to move
towards that extreme so if anything the
prospect of peace and a lasting peace
seems further away than perhaps it ever
has been first I would say something
that may surprise you I read a good
analysis leftist analysis of the
situation in France and Belgium and they
discovered the same thing there among
the I don't like the terms quotation
marks Pro terrorist Arab
immigrants so it's not that they we were
not open enough to integrate them no
most of this young generation of
terrorists who did that concert hall
bombing remember a couple of years ago
in Paris and yeah do you know that there
they are second generation is the same
Paradox that the older generation their
parents were much better integrated into
French uh
Society so uh uh I then the second thing
one has to mention I'm sorry it if it
will sound racist is that a lot of this
younger generation are East European
Jews who are from Russia and other East
European countries who tend to be much
more aggressive racist than the than
than uh the first generation there
really is something
very dark this is the true dark side of
the East European till 89 communism for
example maybe you know the story I spoke
with a German dissident I don't like him
too much but okay he was well known W
Beerman singer who imig at to the West
friend of bre and so on and he told me
that in early 90s immediately after the
reunification he went to some big
ecological meeting in X East Germany and
there was there a strong group of well
to call them by their name
Neo-Nazi Echo people ecologically or and
he told them but you are for Hitler you
know what answer he got he told me one
of the most terrifying answers that I
got no we criticize Hitler because
Hitler did some good things like getting
rid of the Jews but also he developed
car industry he built uh highways and so
on which was horrible you know this most
obscene version so uh this is what
always surprised me that even now even
now the right wing Neo-Nazi parties are
much stronger in X East Germany than in
the west this is what again really makes
me uh really makes me a pessimist that
what you described as something going on
among the Israeli youth is also going on
uh among the Palestinians up to a point
even in the United States look all of
these proud boys and so on and so on and
uh what really makes me afraid is that
liberal democracy the way we knew it is
coming to an end let's for a moment
forget about West Bank Israel let's move
to the United States I think United
States it's really in danger on the edge
of the Civil War I forget his name
because he's a disgusting nobody who is
now the new house speaker oh yeah um was
it it's not McCarthy is it it's um the
new one young one yeah but he's like the
the trumpist um yeah but the ultra Trump
is if you Trump Is We I I'll tell you
yeah yeah I'll tell you after people
like him and the santis we will even
have I predict a Nostalgia for Trump
because Trump was very careful you know
not to pass a certain limit because this
guy openly advocates violating the
Constitution problematizing democracy
people notice very nicely that he never
refers to the United States as democracy
he always uses the term
republic Republic in this Christian
fundamentalist sense and so on and so on
so I don't have a good Counterpoint to
you my Counterpoint is much more sad is
that the whole world is moving in this
Direction look at the catastrophe barely
avoided if it is avoided remember a
couple of weeks ago the first round of
the presidential elections in Argentina
where I again I prefer to erase the
names of really bad people some
right-wing liberal populist yeah again
he went to the end a nightmare and I
always use this when people ask me about
Freedom you know since I also published
by Bloom book on freedom and I try not
to relativize the term of freedom but to
see many dimensions contradictory he
radicalizes this guy something with M
the notion of Freedom did you read I
couldn't believe my eyes when I read it
I had you know I like this scene from
old cartoons Tom and Jerry when you see
something and your eyes jump out and
turn the air you know what he Advocates
he said this is a new freedom to solve
people from poverty to give to poor
people the right to sell their organs
and their children sorry this is liberal
capitalism today and so I that's the
cause of my pessimism yesterday at a
debate on that strange place I liked it
Royal Institute you know uh somebody
attacked me along these lines with a
very good question no somebody told me
uh uh like but your messages we are
up no trouble but you in any case
you are old you will soon die so you
don't care what about the majority of
young people here can
you shouldn't you give them some hope in
my Counterpoint
was that his question is very ambiguous
does he mean that that it's true that we
are up just out of respect for
innocent and young people we should give
them some hope I totally oppose this
this means patronizing them or does he
mean there is hope your analysis is
wrong and I would like to believe I am
that there is some hope my motto is the
one from old Frankfurt School Mark
schimer says this a propo of Nazism that
our STS today should be optim pessimism
in theory optimis in practice and I try
to follow it I'm generally a pessimist
but whenever there is a chance whatever
to do I was engaged against Putin for
for Riot and so on I I I'm in
contact with this may surprise you with
uh with some Guerilla group in
Philippines and so on wherever I quite
liked arist in jron arist in
he was dirtily manipulated by the United
States he was not a crazy Castro likee
utopian he was very modest honest but it
was too much so for a long time I
supported
CA and I still am not sure could they my
reproach to them is again moderately
conservative because they complained how
the European Union treated them but what
did they expect you know yeah like I I
think that absolutely use any of in
India there I'm for Muslims engaged in
things against the horror that Modi is
doing now Modi is playing the same game
As Trump and the new
right some people protested non-hindus
that they don't feel safe you know what
was Mod's answer public Mod's answer was
yeah and it's good so so that you will
know that you are the threat of the
nation and so on it's literal falling
apart of this basic safety of the public
order now in my old age this may sound
horrible to you but the right is today
the one which is more and more populist
violent and so on and I think now I will
say something shocking to you it's an
old story but maybe I hope you are not
an idiot not to you but for others uh
maybe the left should begin to use the
term Moral
Majority look many people I don't think
there were most anti-semites who
demonstrated here hundreds of thousand
and there are for Palestine and there
are probably many more who are afraid to
my friends Israeli friends are now
arrested in Israel and so on we should
address them we should maybe drop
this violence public violence speech and
no my image of the United States is this
one with a little bit of irony but I
think it's
true look my old story when on the 6th
of January the Trump
mob occupied the Congress my leftist
friends were crying we should have been
doing it this is our I told them no
sorry you live in the wrong time today
the game the rules of the game have
changed if we mean by postmodernism this
cynical
relativism flirting with violence blah
blah then if there ever was a postmodern
president historicist relativist it's
Donald Trump and let's face it if there
ever was a person who embodies at its
best the this uh Moral Majority simple
in a progressive sense let's say
conservative in the sense of there
should be basic decency attitude is need
Bernie
Sanders I think we should not leave all
these voters to the new right I didn't
meet Sanders himself but I spoke with
his Ghost Writer with some people around
him who told me Bernie knows this he
Bernie said when there were elections uh
Trump versus
Hillary he said something ingenious he
said don't worry about because Democrats
under Hillary fell into this trap they
worried about the middle will we if we
come to radical
alienate the this undecided middle
classes Bernie said no we should aim at
Trump's voters many of them are
disillusioned poor whites and so on they
should be our our Target that would be
if you ask me my politics today just uh
finally because time is short and you
have to go i' I'd also like to talk to
you briefly about culture and about well
some of the biggest cinematic releases
that we've had this year you've written
already an essay comparing Barbie and
Oppenheimer and I wonder uh this now you
really want to push me into suicide
public
suicide must be interesting movies you
know because I haven't seen them you
know yeah of course yeah no no no I just
like to read reviews and then react and
then react you know okay I'll make I'll
qualify it a little bit I was tempted to
see Barbie yeah because I quite liked
her earlier movies by Greta gerwick you
know she's serious she did some good
things as for Christopher Nolan I'm
ambiguous there I liked the
although who which was his last uh
Batman the one where basically yeah with
no what I like is the idea although he's
against it that Manhattan becomes the
People's Republic LEF his Terror and he
shows his cards there that he is a
reformist but nonetheless the topics was
so daring that you know the guy played
by Tom Hardy yeah the brutal terrorist
no Batman he's there the opponent Bane
Bane yeah but isn't he the only
passionate sympathetic image in the
movie he really loves that woman and
sacrifices his life for her so uh as for
Oppenheimer no I will repeat what I said
yesterday something that horrifies many
of my
friends I saw the movie later not when I
wrote the text you know which part I
liked surprisingly the political part
you know all that the committee in the
committee and committee how they
manipulate opener and these double games
and so on how he is in advance
sacrificed what I hate hate
is bhavat Gita because I mentioned this
yesterday read history of
ss hinry himler the most disgusting guy
uh he always carried in his pocket get a
special letter bound version of Bhagavad
Gita why because he was aware himler he
was well aware that as a SS officer you
have to do horrible thing killing
helpless starve juice and his problem
was an ethical one ironic as this may
sound how can you do it without losing
your dignity and his answer was Bhagavad
Gita you know this idea of don't be
identified with your acts learn to act
at a distance and so on so I don't like
that reference to Bhagavad Gita so you
remember the first sex scene
uher with Florence Pew yeah the
Communist mistress not yet the wife and
uh she asks him or who whom I don't know
to read Bhagavad Gita and you remember
there was an outcry in India yes I agree
with them but in the opposite sense why
yes I'm against that because how could
they spoil a beautiful sex act with a
porno dirty book like bav gu you Christ
and I mean I I'm not alone here I'm not
alone here with all my Indian friends
sure I we agree what I already mentioned
uh the greatest strategy in India was
that around year zero in our Chris era
you know you know all of a sudden uh
Hinduism made a successful return and
Buddhism disappeared and uh many uh of
my Indian friends even radical leftist
respect much more than Gandhi ambedkar
who was the great anti cast liberal
Gandhi was never again casts he just
said each cast has its own dignity
they're all children of got it's the
same thing as fascists are saying
working class also has its proper place
and dignity and so on and so on so in
this sense I must say uh I enjoyed the
movie but I didn't like this Pudo
metaphysical background forget about
that SL thank you so much for taking the
time to speak to me it's been pleasure
I'm grateful to you and uh uh I'm very
sorry concluding joke if you're still on
that I like you are not active enough
because you know when people ask me
about dialogue I'm violent you know it's
my standard answer I like dialogues but
like late plat dialogues where one guy
talks all the time and the other guy
just say every 10 no no every 10 minutes
by Z so it is Socrates and so on I like
the my favorite part of our speech today
dialogue is that once I did provoke you
into stri in back a little bit you know
yeah I am you should maybe even if we
will have another opportunity no let's
put it in this way I cannot avoid
obscenities no yeah of course I would
like to we go on well let's consider
this an intellectual not sexual
Quicky let's do another one more you
know kutra yeah we'll do kutra version
yeah long long form yeah but Also let's
not go into it because with Kamasutra I
also have problems you know it's for me
the ultimate book that ruins
sexuality SL voice thank you so much I'm
I'm really grateful to you because I was
told you were a nice surprise for me
because I mobilized my small private KGB
Spy Service no and there was oh he makes
jokes no you're not an idiot although
you make jokes and so on you you have a
mind you know thank you that's high
prize thank you very much that's high
prize mate thank you okay happy guys
phooo you up your from the s or
whatever oh my
gosh